GORDON: Previously on Gotham...
LEE: What's your record for how
many banks you've robbed in one day?
You're playing a
dangerous game, Lee.
LEE: My job is to make sure that
the people of The Narrows are safe.
And I will do everything
in my power to ensure that.
GORDON: I'm
looking for Ed Nygma.
Five banks were
robbed last night.
Why don't you try going
after the real criminals?
Making money off
the backs of the poor?
GORDON: Like Gotham
Savings and Loan?
You are a fool!
GORDON: Come out
with your hands up!
I expected you
might come, Captain.
There's two of them.
HARVEY: What if he's
nuttier than the other one?
JEREMIAH: I'm
nothing like Jerome!
I'm gonna drive you mad.
But don't worry, all of
Gotham will be joining you.
- GORDON: Hands up!
- Bombs away!
JEROME: I'm more
than a man, I'm an idea,
and I will live on
in the shadows,
within Gotham's discontent.
JEROME: Burn it down, brother.
(LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
MAN: Brothers and sisters,
let's raise a glass
to our fallen leader.
To Jerome!
ALL: To Jerome!
(GARGLING AND SPITTING)
(ENGINE REVVING)
(ENGINE STOPS)
This affair is invitation only.
(BELLS JINGLING)
Well, that's all right,
you're welcome to stay.
But you won't be leaving.
(HORN HONKING LOUDLY)
(INDISTINCT GROANING)
JEROME: Why so sad, bozos?
Did you think they could
get rid of me so easily?
Well, okay. So, they did.
I'm dead, but let's
not dwell on negatives.
I have one last party to throw.
- First on the to-do
list, - (ALL LAUGHING)
dig me up.
Dig me up!
MAN: You heard him!
Come on, clowns! Dig him up!
Get Jerome!
We're gonna dig you
up, Jerome! You hear me?
Come on out of there!
Come on, dig, dig, dig!
- What are you gonna do?
- What can I do?
The back door's just down
that hallway right there.
- I'm not letting her go, Harvey.
- Why not?
I'm the only one here.
And I'm really good at
looking the other way, partner.
Not this time.
She robbed a dirty bank.
People get away with a lot
worse in Gotham every day.
Doesn't make it right.
We got away with
worse. Both of us.
Get out of here.
What?
I don't need that crap
thrown in my face right now.
Get out of here!
(DOOR OPENS)
Well, you finally
nabbed me, copper.
(SIGHS) What the hell, Lee?
I don't suppose this is where
anyone expected our story to end.
So, it's ending?
Hard to imagine what's left.
I wanna help you.
- How?
- Give up Nygma.
Return the money, and ask
the DA for supervised probation.
I'm not betraying my friend.
They can call you "the Doc,"
you can rob banks, fight
gangsters, but I know you.
You're Lee Thompkins.
And all this, this is just a...
A way of helping people.
I understand that.
Who doesn't want to be Robin
Hood? But you're still breaking the law.
Jim, you wish you
could do what I'm doing.
Helping people without
the straitjacket of the law?
As if the law means
anything in Gotham.
If the law has lost its meaning,
it's because people like you
are turning your back on it.
I am fighting back. I don't
deny anything I've done.
You want to send me
to Blackgate? Go ahead.
I don't want to send you to Blackgate!
It's the last thing I want to do!
Don't you know I wish I
could let you walk out that door,
- turn my head...
- What's holding you back?
(EXHALES)
Maybe if you'd let me go,
you'd let yourself go, too.
There are so many things
I wish I could change.
Things that I've done...
Jim...
(KNOCK AT DOOR)
(DOOR OPENS)
Sorry to stick my face in your
business, but something just came up.
I've already inspected
it for booby traps.
- It's clear.
- Well, that's a relief.
I've taken the liberty of setting
up a monitor in your office.
(ORGAN MUSIC PLAYING)
You don't think he might
still be alive, do you?
What were the
autopsy results, Lucius?
Dead when he came in, more
dead when he was eviscerated,
and his brain was sliced up.
Hello, Jimmy!
If you're watching this,
things must not
have gone well for me.
Shucks! (CHUCKLES)
I can only pray, I
gave as good as I got,
and left ample
carnage in my wake.
But I don't want to fixate
on disappointments.
Jimmy, I have one last
teensy request for you.
I want you to throw me a wake
at the GCPD.
(AUDIO SCRAMBLING)
Don't worry about the guest list.
I've already sent
the invitations.
(LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
I don't like the sound of that.
- (HORN HONKING)
- (PEOPLE SHOUTING)
Is everybody ready?
(MOB CHEERING)
Lock down everything, now!
Everybody listen up! Lock
it down! Lock it down, now!
(CAR HORN HONKING)
The Doc's taken care of us.
It's time for us to take care of her!
Let's go down there,
and bust her out of jail.
No one cares about the fate of
Lee Thompkins more than me,
is that understood?
Which is exactly why I will not have
you bumbling into the GCPD en masse.
So, we're going to let her rot?
Leave her in the sweaty
palms of Jim Gordon?
I would sooner debate you all
on teleology versus deontology,
than leave her with that
overgrown Boy Scout.
"Teleo..." Huh?
My point exactly.
Look, if I had it my way,
Jim Gordon would be off the
field of play once and for all.
But Lee insists that I
employ only nonlethal means.
So, I and my
brilliant crack team
will liberate Lee Thompkins
with surgical precision.
You stay here.
Team, we have everything?
- Bicycle pump? Can opener?
- Right here.
Primer cord? Pickle
jar? Fishing rod?
Fabulous. Okay, you
four, you're with me.
You, go where Jim Gordon goes.
He comes under
some harm, assist him.
I do not need Lee blaming me
if he's killed under friendly fire,
while I go about
my business, okay?
All right, team, follow my plan,
and we'll be back here
to finish counting this
in just a few hours. Keep it up.
Breaking Lee out is
going to be a piece of cake.
(TELEPHONE RINGING)
Hello, Wayne Manor.
Alfred, it's Gordon.
Where's Bruce?
Well, he's meeting with
Jeremiah about the energy project.
Is something amiss?
He's meeting with
Jeremiah Valeska?
Yes, that's right.
Now, you can tell me why
you sound so concerned.
Jerome's followers are
rampaging outside the station.
Oh, I see.
Are Master Bruce and
Jeremiah in any danger?
It's hard to say. But right now,
Jeremiah's maze may actually
be the safest place for him.
Right, I shall head there
nonetheless. Thank you very much.
- (THUDDING)
- (PEOPLE SHOUTING)
What's the plan?
- Open up the armory.
- Now you're talkin'.
Guys!
(MAN LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
- (GUNS COCKING)
- HARVEY: Jim! Hey, Jim!
You figure out when
we're going to hit 'em yet?
- We're not.
- Say what?
You know how Jerome works,
dead or alive.
He uses distractions.
So, what, we're
going to just let 'em
come in through the
front door and party?
This wake is just
intended to distract us,
while his followers
hit the real target.
- Which is?
- Well,
we're never gonna
figure that out
if we're inside, fighting
off these maniacs, are we?
Look, they come in
the front door, right?
You fall back, get a few
shots off, make it look good.
Meanwhile, the entire precinct
sneaks out this old service
door as quickly as possible.
I can't believe you're going
to run away from these asses.
Once we're outside, we
surround the building, cordon it off.
- And then we trap 'em all inside.
- Correct. They blow off some steam.
We hit 'em with teargas,
and knock a few heads.
Yeah. Of course, we
still have to figure out
what the real target is.
Got a plan for that?
I do.
It's a little sketchy
right now, but come on.
All right, listen up, people!
Here's the plan.
Jeremiah,
I didn't think you could get the
generator program working so quickly.
You ready for a demonstration?
Okay, you hit that switch there,
and the facility will be
disconnected from the power grid.
(GENERATOR POWERING UP)
(ELECTRICITY BUZZING)
Ambient energy.
No cables or wires of any
kind. It's clean and stable.
Harvested from micro tremors
and air density shifts, it's...
It's virtually without costs.
And with the prototypes at Wayne
Labs, we can power all of Gotham?
You've kept this
project a secret, yes?
No one outside of Wayne
Industries knows it exists.
It's the ones who
are closest to you
(WHISPERING) that you
have to keep your eye on.
I know better than anyone.
Arkham Asylum sent me
Jerome's personal effects,
and amongst them,
I found his diary.
It's a catalog of his
fantasies and goals.
Every twisted
vision he ever had.
Maybe you shouldn't spend
so much time reading it.
He was obsessed with torturing and
murdering me, James Gordon, and you,
and if he had been
just the least bit sane,
he would have destroyed us all.
And Gotham would be in ruin.
Your brother's dead, Jeremiah.
It's time for you to come out of
this bunker and join the world.
Yes.
Yes, he's dead.
- I still have trouble believing it.
- (PHONE VIBRATING)
Who is that?
It's just Alfred.
Yeah?
Master Bruce, I've got
some rather disturbing news.
Jerome Valeska's acolytes
are kicking off again.
Yes.
- Thank you, Alfred.
- I'm on my way.
Lunch plans.
That was a lie.
You're lying to me, Bruce?
You're right. I'm sorry.
It seems some of Jerome's
followers are causing trouble.
Oh, my God. I was right.
No, Jeremiah.
I was right. He's not dead.
Bruce, he's not dead. He's
alive, and he's coming after me!
(GLASS SHATTERING)
(GRUNTING AND SCREAMING)
(GUNSHOTS)
Jeremiah, easy, easy.
You're not thinking clearly.
- Come on, this isn't like you.
- Bruce...
Bruce, I need to
tell you something.
After Jerome died, he left
one last final trap for me.
He sprayed me
with his insanity gas.
"It's a special mixture just
for you, brother," he said.
I can't stop seeing him.
Clawing his way
out of his grave,
coming for me, and even
though I know it's not real,
it feels real.
And I can't control myself.
What if I could show
you he's dead and buried?
How?
- We go there, to his grave.
- No.
- No, no, no.
- Jeremiah, listen to me.
Your brother took away
your greatest strength,
your mind, and
turned it into a trap.
But if you can see the reality,
you can be freed from that trap.
You really think
that would work?
I do.
Then I'll try.
You're a good friend, Bruce.
(PEOPLE GRUNTING AND SHOUTING)
I'm getting you and the
other prisoners out of here.
What were you trying
to tell me before, Jim?
There's a van outside,
waiting for transfer.
- Don't ignore me.
- I just want to get you safe first.
- Come to The Narrows.
- What?
Where you can make a
real difference in this city.
You can make up your
own rules about how to do it.
(PEOPLE SHOUTING)
(LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
- Alvarez, get them out of here. Go.
- (ALARM BLARING)
Don't shoot! Hold your fire.
- (PEOPLE SHOUTING)
- (CHAINSAW WHIRRING)
There's too many
of them. Fall back!
Fall back!
Let's go! Let's go!
(LAUGHING)
Well, look at us.
We caught ourselves
Captain James Gordon.
Assassin of Jerome Valeska.
Hi, guys.
Don't try and get
chummy with us, Gordon.
We're gonna carve you up.
Yeah, no, I wasn't talkin'
to you. I was talkin' to them.
- Hey, man, you like to dance?
- (ELECTRICITY BUZZING)
(FOLLOWERS GROANING)
Let's you and me talk
outside, what do you say?
(PHONE RINGING AND VIBRATING)
(PHONE RINGING)
- There's still no answer.
- Then something's wrong.
- We should go.
- He was on his way to your office.
He'll wait for us there.
(TWIGS SNAPPING)
What was that?
(THUNDER CRACKING)
We're almost there. Just a
quick look, and we'll leave.
Bruce. Bruce.
I don't know if I can do this.
Just a little further.
Oh, God, no.
His followers must
have dug him up.
He's still alive.
I knew it.
- We have to get out of here.
- I knew it.
- He's alive!
- Jeremiah! Jeremiah!
(BOTH GRUNTING)
How much longer are these petty
aggressions going to continue?
There's nothing petty
about my aggression.
So, am I to starve until I guess
the source of your resentment?
You said if I joined
you, we'd be back on top.
Instead, we're grubbing for
Jerome, and we got played by Nygma.
You said if I joined you,
you'd find me a cure. And, yet...
I admit, that through
no fault of my own,
our advancement
has not run apace.
(SHOUTS) "Not run apace"?
We're squatting in
Falcone's mansion.
We're knockin' over liquor
stores to pay for groceries.
Meanwhile, everyone else
is carving up Sofia's territory.
We are lying in wait,
building a nest egg,
while less deliberate
players show us their cards.
If you don't find me Hugo
Strange and get me cured,
I am going to crush your
windpipe like a beer can.
Shh!
- Did you just shush me?
- Shush! I sense an opportunity here.
(REPORTER ON TV)
live to Jennifer Glory.
In a twist that Jerome Valeska
himself could've thought of,
the GCPD are laying
siege to Central Precinct,
while Valeska's followers hold a
wake for their deceased role model.
How is that an opportunity?
Confusion is always an
opportunity for the clearheaded.
Someone is showing their
cards, Butch. Let's go take a peek.
(GRUMBLES)
(HELICOPTER HOVERING)
(REPORTERS CHATTERING)
One to the east, one
to the west. Let's go.
- Is he talkin' yet?
- I don't know, let's check.
MAN: Long live Jerome!
HARVEY: All right.
One more time, sunshine.
Did Jerome leave
any other instructions?
- I'll never...
- (TASER BUZZING)
Harvey! Harvey!
Reporters, buddy.
All right, look, this is
how it's going to go.
You're going to start talking,
or I'm gonna stop caring
whether you can talk, you got it?
(MAN GROANING AND SCREAMING)
I'll talk!
It's too late, anyways.
They're already dead.
Who? Who's dead?
Jeremiah and Bruce Wayne.
- You think he's tellin' the truth?
- I'm gonna find out.
They're at Jeremiah's bunker.
You hold down the fort here?
MAN: Long live Jerome!
- (TASER BUZZING)
- (MAN SCREAMING)
(SIREN BLARING IN DISTANCE)
- Trouble, Mr. Riddler?
- A complication, yes.
Hostiles take over the station.
Police will remove the
prisoners. Where are they?
(THUDDING)
Oh, yes. This might be
easier than I expected.
(LAUGHING)
The Riddler! We're saved!
How did you get out?
Through the old service door.
The old service door.
- What do we do, now?
- Now we improvise.
They're going to use
teargas in here soon.
I have to get in first. We
need a costume shop. Quick!
Penguin! We're saved!
- That one.
- Jerome...
No, not the trunk...
You ever get tired
of being wrong?
(PEOPLE SCREAMING
AND CHATTERING)
(DOOR OPENING)
(THUNDER RUMBLING)
Jeremiah!
We need to leave! It's not safe!
JEREMIAH: You believe me now?
Jerome's alive!
No, his followers dug
him up. They're sick!
They're also dangerous,
and they might be nearby!
How can I trust you if
you won't believe me?
You can trust me
because I'm your friend.
I want you to be
my friend, Bruce.
You don't know what it was like,
living underground
all those years.
Then you came along and offered
me everything I could dream of.
Because I believe
in you, Jeremiah.
We're gonna do great
things for Gotham.
We could. We really could.
I thought we would.
There's no reason
to stop thinking that.
All we have to do,
is get out of here.
First, all we had to do
was come to the cemetery.
Now all we have to do is leave?
See, that's very
confusing to me.
So, tell me again, Bruce,
why'd you really bring me here?
I thought it would help.
I was wrong. But
we need to leave.
(SHOUTS) What the
hell are you doing?
You think I didn't know
what was happening
from the moment you
suggested coming here?
- Jeremiah, what are you talking...
- Stop pretending to be my friend!
I know what's really happening.
You can fool everyone else,
but I know you made a switch.
That, you can't hide.
Not even behind
that new face of yours.
I know it's you.
I know it's you, Jerome.
Jeremiah, give me the gun.
(GUNSHOT)
Turn around, brother.
I said turn around! You
killed my friend Bruce.
Now it's time to put
you back in your grave.
Walk!
(PEOPLE SCREAMING
AND CHATTERING)
(STUTTERING)
(LAUGHS NERVOUSLY)
- (POT CLANGS)
- (GRUNTS)
Ed!
(DOOR OPENS)
Bruce? Jeremiah?
(STATIC BUZZING)
Just a little bit further, brother.
Then you'll be back in your grave.
You're stronger
than this, Jeremiah.
You know these ideas are
just the insanity gas talking.
I won't let your lies
fool me any longer!
(GASPING)
What is happening?
- Hiya, Jimbo!
- Jerome...
Ah!
Don't bother talkin' to me.
This is a recorded message,
and plus, I'm still dead.
Just more posthumous fun.
Look, I knew you'd see through
all those shenanigans at the station.
I've given all my fans a
script for them to follow.
See,
I wanted to bring you here.
Oh!
(JEROME LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
Now do you believe
I'm not your brother?
Jeremiah, listen to me!
Jerome's followers
are doing this!
Nothing else makes sense.
He sent them
instructions to torment you.
How fake.
Yes, I can see quite clearly
where you cut off poor Bruce's face,
and stitched on your own.
But I am a man of science.
So, let's have some
evidence, huh?
Oh!
Don't mind her.
She's just here to make sure
there's no talking during the movie.
And, trust me, you're
gonna wanna pay attention,
so the twist makes
sense at the end.
(LAUGHS EVILLY)
(CHOKING)
(GORDON GRUNTING)
Let's go, brother. Let's pull
off that grotesque facade.
(JEREMIAH GRUNTING)
Ecco.
(JEROME CHOKING)
I tell you,
suicide really takes it out
of a guy. (CHUCKLING)
What is this?
Jeremiah! Do not let
him turn you into him!
- Do not let Jerome win this battle!
- (JEROME STRAINING)
Jerome, beat me?
That'll be the day.
No!
(JEREMIAH LAUGHING)
Long live Jerome!
- Long live Jerome!
Jerome is victorious at last!
Jerome victorious?
Are you serious?
He's dead.
Haven't you been
paying attention?
JEREMIAH: Thank
God I'm done with that.
I am the one who's victorious.
Jerome is dead.
(ECHOING) Is dead... Is dead.
Long live... Long live me.
Long live me.
Look, Bruce,
like everything Jerome set his
mind to, his insanity gas failed.
Other than some
mild cosmetic effects,
he might as well have
sprayed me with water.
You all need to see Jerome
for the utter dud that he was.
So, I donned the mask of madness
to show you how feeble that is
compared to actual greatness.
Behold, the face of true sanity.
But looks aren't everything.
I have a compendium of
Jerome's obsessions and goals.
I will outdo every one of them.
Jerome wanted to turn
Gotham into a madhouse.
But to truly build something,
you must first tear down
what is already there.
JEREMIAH: I apologize
for the deception, Jim.
I needed to ape Jerome
in order to persuade
his followers to throw that
macabre celebration
at your police station.
They are a pathetic lot,
but not without their uses.
(DOOR LOCKING)
Sidebar, that is a
self-perpetuating generator.
It can store a phenomenal
amount of energy.
I would hate to be within a
mile of it if it were to overload.
BRUCE: Jeremiah, the gas worked.
Think about it. You want to carry
out Jerome's crazy plans sanely?
- What could be madder than that?
- "Madder"?
Let's see.
Ah, here, for example.
Jerome wanted to
slather you in honey,
and have you eaten
alive by corpse beetles.
Now, that's mad.
Me, if I wanna kill
you, I'll just do it.
I'll shoot you in the
head. (COCKING GUN)
Simply and sanely.
- (FOLLOWERS TITTERING)
- Jeremiah...
But I don't want to kill you.
(FOLLOWERS GROANING)
Are you gonna listen, or are
you gonna behave like children?
See, I don't want to kill you,
because I wanna show you
how much I've changed things.
How much we've changed things.
Because I could not
have done any of this
without your help.
My help?
JEREMIAH: That
sound you are hearing,
(GENERATOR BUZZING)
that is a very bad sound.
One which, I'm afraid,
makes you something
of a guinea pig, Jim.
JEREMIAH: I feel very
indebted to you, Bruce.
See, those generators that
we built with your money,
they work even better as bombs.
(BEEPING)
Killing you will help secure
the loyalty of Jerome's minions.
And, well...
That is that.
Goodbye.
All right, everybody, listen
up! You know what to do!
Let's go get our house back!
(DISTANT EXPLOSION)
(ALARM BLARING)
That's one down.
- Jim Gordon is dead.
- (FOLLOWERS CHEERING)
- No! No!
- Yes, Bruce.
Sorry, but progress
requires sacrifice.
I'm going to stop you.
I really hope you don't try. I
would hate to have to kill you.
In fact, I can honestly say,
you are my very best friend.
What I want to know,
with a minimum of fuss,
is what you and your cohort
were really up to today?
I'll never betray
the memory of...
Wouldn't dream of it.
I don't expect you to betray
the memory of that old corpse.
I want you to betray whomever
it is you are currently following.
- Long live Jerome.
- He's not talking.
Is that so?
You starin' at me?
Yeah, I get it.
Sometimes, I accidentally catch
a glimpse of myself in the mirror.
It scares me, too.
And then I get angry.
The longer I'm like
this, the angrier I get.
And right now, the way I see it,
you are preventing
me from finding a cure.
And that
makes me very, very angry.
Is your plan to gain his sympathy
by reciting your tale of woe?
Nah. Just wanted to see if I could get
him to pee his pants a little in terror.
You want me to shove some chicken
bones up his nose till he squawks?
- Yes, that will do.
- No.
Let's make this quick.
(STRAINING)
- Tilt your head back.
- No!
- Here comes the wishbone train!
- No, no! (SCREAMING)
Smartest man in Gotham, and
you let your heart do the thinking.
Wake up, Ed!
Ow!
- Were you awake the whole time?
- Maybe.
"The smartest man
in Gotham," huh?
All right, get up. Up, up, up.
There are better things
to aspire to, you know.
I'm aspiring to them
very much. (BLOWS)
Just be yourself.
The guy who can let go
of the past and change,
I like that guy.
All right, now, how are we
going to get past these psychos?
I'm assuming you brought
one of those for me?
No. I'd be into that,
but they only had one.
Instead...
- The cavalry should be coming very soon.
- Great.
- (ROCK MUSIC PLAYING)
- (PEOPLE CHATTERING)
(TEAR GAS SHELLS HISSING)
(PEOPLE SHOUTING AND COUGHING)
- Round them up!
- (GUNS COCKING)
Move, move, move! Let's go!
Okay.
Don't just wrap me
around your finger, Lee.
Come on, let's run.
(GRUNTS)
That's for takin' a
leak on my desk.
What a mess.
You know, it's funny,
it kind of reminds me of my
first apartment in Crown Point.
How long ago was that?
- I still live there.
- GORDON: Harvey.
I found the epicenter
of that explosion.
It's Jeremiah's bunker.
That's where Jim was
going to look for Bruce.
- Good evening, gentlemen.
- Hey there, Mr. Valeska.
You alone, or you got
Mr. Wayne with you?
No Mr. Wayne.
But I'm not alone.
What the...
Look at these. The
gifts of true friendship.
Let's load them on the trucks.
It's time to give Gotham
City its new face.